Register of the Juan Domingo Perón papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Juan Domingo Perón papers
1931-2002
89011
Hoover Institution Archives
10 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes (5.4 linear feet)
The Juan Domingo Perón papers consist primarily of correspondence between Perón and his followers, conducted largely during the period of his exile in Madrid, Spain. Among the correspondents are many of the major figures of the Peronist movement, including trade union leaders in Argentina and exiled Peronist activists. The letters themselves contain detailed information about rivalries and intrigues among different Peronist factions, and they record the efforts of Perón's lieutenants as they sought both to curry favor in the eyes of their leader and to sustain the Peronist movement within Argentina. They also document the roles played by Isabel Perón and José Lopez Rega in the last years of Juan Perón's life.
Perón, Juan Domingo, 1895-1974.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in intervals between 1958 and 2004.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1895 Born, Province of Buenos Aires, Argentina
1911-1937 Entered military school, after graduation served in armed forces
1938 Sent to Europe as a military observer; visited Italy and was favorably impressed by Benito Mussolini's fascist government
1943 Participated in military coup against civilian government of Ramón Castillo and became head of Department of Labor
1945 February Became Vice President and Secretary of War
1945 October Married Eva Duarte, known as Evita Perón
1946 Elected President of Argentina
1952 Served second term as president
1955 September Overthrown in military coup
1955-1972 Lived in exile, first in Panama and then in the Dominican Republic, eventually settling in Madrid, Spain
1961 Married María Estela Martínez, known as Isabel Perón
1973 Returned to Argentina and was elected president
1974 Died. Isabel Perón succeeded him as president
Scope and Content of Collection
The Juan Domingo Perón papers consist primarily of correspondence between Perón and his followers, conducted largely during the period of his exile in Madrid, Spain. Among the correspondents are many of the major figures of the Peronist movement, including trade union leaders in Argentina and exiled Peronist activists. The letters themselves contain detailed information about rivalries and intrigues among different Peronist factions, and they record the efforts of Perón's lieutenants as they sought both to curry favor in the eyes of their leader and to sustain the Peronist movement within Argentina. They also document the roles played by Isabel Perón and José Lopez Rega in the last years of Juan Perón's life.
A significant part of the Correspondence series consists of letters exchanged between Perón and Pablo Vicente, a former colonel in the Argentinian army living in exile in Montevideo, Uruguay, who acted as a conduit for mail being sent to Perón from his followers in Argentina. These letters from supporters were left as they were originally arranged, among the correspondence from Vicente to Perón. Vicente's letters to Perón also include detailed analyses of political developments in Argentina, as well as Vicente's own assessments of internal tensions within the Peronist movement.
Other notable correspondents include John W. Cooke, who at one time seemed to be Perón's heir apparent. The major Peronist labor organizations, including the 62 Organizaciones, figure in the correspondence, as does the Consejo Coordinador y Supervisor de Peronismo. There are letters and reports sent to Perón by one of the earliest Peronist guerrilla movements, the Fuerzas Armadas Peronistas (FAP), as well as one letter from the much larger armed Peronist organization, the Montoneros. The series also has two drafts of a significant letter sent by Perón to President John F. Kennedy, then newly-elected, in 1961.
The papers contain a number of articles and speeches by Perón, and these are described in the Speeches and Writings series. This series also includes the outlines of lectures given by Perón in the 1930s on the Russo-Japanese War of 1905. Less important writings by Perón, such as communiqués and memoranda, are grouped in the Peronist Movement File, which also contains materials relating to Isabel Perón and Jose Lopez Rega. This file has a short handwritten declaration by Evita Perón as well.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into eight series: Biographical file, Correspondence, Speeches and Writings, Peronist Movement File, Subject File, Photographs, Printed Matter, and Oversize Materials.
Related Material
Juan Atilio Bramuglia papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Luis Fernando Calviño papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Américo Ghioldi papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Hipólito Jesus Paz papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Argentina--Politics and government--1943-; Statesmen--Argentina.
- Biographical File, 1955-1972 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes article and clippings, certificate of copyright, legal and tax records, arranged alphabetically by physical form.
  - Article and clippings, 1966-1972 (File 1: 1)
  - Certificate of copyright, 1955 (File 1: 2)
  - Hotel registration card, circa 1960 (File 1: 3)
  - Legal records pertaining to the appeal of a ruling against the presidential candidacy of Juan Perón, 1972 (File 1: 4)
  - Tax records, 1963-1967 (File 1: 5)
- Correspondence, 1954-1974 (Boxes 1-8)
  Letters and enclosures, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - General, 1957-1973
    - A, 1958-1972 (File 1: 6)
    - B, 1958-1972 (File 1: 7)
    - C, 1958-1973 (File 1: 8)
    - D, 1959-1972 (File 1: 9)
    - E, 1967-1973 (File 1: 10)
    - F, 1958-1972 (File 1: 11)
    - G, 1960-1973 (File 1: 12)
    - H-I, 1959-1972 (File 1: 13)
    - J-K, 1959-1973 (File 1: 14)
    - L, 1959-1973 (File 1: 15)
    - M, 1959-1973 (File 1: 16)
    - N-O, 1959-1973 (File 1: 17)
    - P, 1959-1973 (File 1: 18)
    - R, 1957-1973 (File 1: 19)
    - S, 1958-1972 (File 1: 20)
    - T, 1958-1972 (File 2: 1)
    - U-V, 1958-1972 (File 2: 2)
    - W-Z, 1963-1972 (File 2: 3)
  - Unidentified, 1958-1971 (File 2: 4)
  - Alberte, Bernardo, 1967-1968 (File 2: 5)
  - Albrieu, Oscar E., 1958-1959 (File 2: 6)
  - Aloé, Carlos, 1958-1972 (File 2: 7)
  - Alonso, José, 1958-1968 (File 2: 8)
  - Amar, Carlos P., 1971 (File 2: 9)
  - Anchorena, Manuel de, 1970-1972 (File 2: 10)
  - Antonio, Jorge, 1965-1972 (File 2: 11)
  - Apold, Paul A., 1971 (File 2: 12)
  - Asseff, Alberto, 1969-1973 (File 2: 13)
  - Balaguer, Joaquín, 1958-1960 (File 2: 14)
  - Baldrich, Alberto, 1965-1970 (File 2: 15)
  - Barbieri, Francisco José, 1967 (File 2: 16)
  - Barrios, Américo, 1960-1964 (File 2: 17)
  - Benitez, Antonio J., 1971-1972 (File 2: 18)
  - Bidegain, Oscar R., 1968-1973 (File 2: 19)
  - Bonino, Alberto C., 1969 (File 2: 20)
  - Borbón, Juan Carlos de, 1973 (File 2: 21)
  - Bramuglia, Carlos Atilio, 1963-1969 (File 2: 22)
  - Bramuglia, Juan Atilio, 1961 (File 2: 23)
  - Brito Lima, Alberto, 1964-1972 (File 2: 24)
  - Cafiero, Antonio, 1965-1973 (File 2: 25)
  - Cámpora, Héctor J., 1972-1973 (File 2: 26)
  - Campos, Alberto, 1959-1960 (File 2: 27)
  - Carril, Hugo del, 1971 (File 3: 1)
  - Casariego, Mario Cardenal, 1972-1973 (File 3: 2)
  - Comisión Argentina "Pro Retorno del General Perón,", 1967-1968 (File 3: 3)
  - Confederación General de los Universitarios, 1960 (File 3: 4)
  - Confederación General del Trabajo, 1958-1972 (File 3: 5)
  - Consejo Coordinador y Supervisor del Peronismo, 1958-1962 (File 3: 6)
  - Cooke, John W., 1958-1964 (File 3: 7)
  - Cruz, Maria de la, 1954-1966 (File 3: 8)
  - Diaz de Vivar, Joaquin, 1971 (File 3: 9)
  - Errecalte, Mario Juan, 1966 (File 3: 10)
  - Farmache, Horacio Alberto, 1968-1972 (File 3: 11)
  - Fatigati, Ernesto G., 1959-1971 (File 3: 12)
  - Figuerola, Francisco José, 1960-1972 (File 3: 13)
  - Framini, Andrés, 1959-1972 (File 3: 14)
  - Frenkel, Leopoldo, 1972 (File 3: 15)
  - Frigerio, Rogelio, 1968-1972 (File 3: 16)
  - Frondizi, Arturo, 1973 (File 3: 17)
  - Fuerzas Armadas Peronistas (FAP), 1969-1971 (File 3: 18)
  - Garcia, Roberto J., 1967 (File 3: 19)
  - Galimberti, Rodolfo, 1972-1973 (File 3: 20)
  - Garcia Mellid, Atilio, 1958-1971 (File 3: 21)
    Includes imperfect English translations of all letters.
  - Giménez Caballero, Ernesto, 1971 (File 3: 22)
  - Güerci, Enrique, 1965-1967 (File 3: 23)
  - Imperatrice, Carlos Alberto, 1967-1969 (File 3: 24)
  - Iñiguez, Miguel Angel, 1954-1971 (File 3: 25)
  - Iturbe, Arturo J., 1961-1971 (File 4: 1)
  - Jáuregui, José Julio, 1967-1968 (File 4: 2)
  - Jaureteche, Arturo M., 1968 (File 4: 3)
  - José, Juan, 1963-1965 (File 4: 4)
  - Kennedy, John F., 1961 (File 4: 5)
  - Labaké, Juan Gabriel, 1988 (File 4: 6)
  - Landajo, Ramón, 1965-1969 (File 4: 7)
  - Leloir, Alejandro H., 1957 (File 4: 8)
  - Licastro, Francisco Julián, 1971 (File 4: 9)
  - Lopez, Adolfo C., 1969-1970 (File 4: 10)
  - Lynch, Marta, circa 1970 (File 4: 11)
  - Macri, Ana C., 1958-1968 (File 4: 12)
  - Matera, Raúl (pseudonym, Martín Cruz)
    - 1963-1965 (File 4: 13)
    - 1966-1971 (File 4: 14)
  - Mayalde, Conde de, 1972-1973 (File 4: 15)
  - Michelini, Pedro Emilio
    - 1965-1967 (File 4: 16)
    - 1968 (File 4: 17)
    - 1969-1972 (File 4: 18)
  - Miel Asquía, Angel J., 1967-1972 (File 4: 19)
  - Miguel, Lorenzo, 1970-1973 (File 4: 20)
  - Minichillo, Juan José, 1968-1971 (File 4: 21)
  - Molina, José Domingo, 1955 (File 4: 22)
  - Montoneros, 1972 (File 4: 23)
  - Movimiento Revolucionario Peronista, 1972 (File 4: 24)
  - Nasser, Gamal Abdel, 1959 (File 4: 25)
  - Neustadt, Bernardo, 1969-1972 (File 4: 26)
  - Nicolini, Chocha, 1965 (File 5: 1)
  - Ongaro, Raimundo José, 1968-1970 (File 5: 2)
  - Osinde, Jorge M., 1965-1972 (File 5: 3)
  - Paladino, Jorge Daniel, 1968-1971 (File 5: 4)
  - Pavón Pereyra, Enrique, 1968 (File 5: 5)
  - Paz, Hipólito, 1959 (File 5: 6)
  - Pepe, Lorenzo A., 1967-1971 (File 5: 7)
  - Pérez Suazo, Aurora, 1961 (File 5: 8)
  - Perón, Isabel, 1961-1972 (File 5: 9)
  - Pettinato, Roberto, 1965-1971 (File 5: 10)
  - Puiggros, Rodolfo, 1959-1970 (File 5: 11)
  - Ramos, Jorge Abelardo, 1968-1970 (File 5: 12)
  - Reed, Dean, 1972 (File 5: 13)
  - Remorino, Jerónimo, 1964-1968 (File 5: 14)
  - Rodríguez, Dora A. P. de, 1964-1974 (File 5: 15)
  - Rojo, Ricardo, 1972-1973 (File 5: 16)
  - Romero, Julio, 1965-1972 (File 5: 17)
  - Rucci, José, 1970-1973 (File 5: 18)
  - Rudel, Hans-Ulrich, circa 1970 (File 5: 19)
  - Saadi, Vicente L., 1968-1972 (File 5: 20)
  - Sánchez Sorondo, Marcelo, 1971-1973 (File 5: 21)
  - Sanchez Toranzo, José A., 1964 (File 5: 22)
  - Sarrabayrouse Varangot, José Ma., 1970-1971 (File 5: 23)
  - 62 Organizaciones, 1958-1971 (File 5: 24)
  - Skorzeny, Otto, 1965 (File 5: 25)
  - Solari, Angel, 1972 (File 5: 26)
  - Solari Yrigoyen, Hipólito, 1967-1968 (File 5: 27)
  - Sosa Molina, Arnaldo, 1959 (File 5: 28)
  - Suárez, Carlos A., 1967-1971 (File 5: 29)
  - Suárez, José Léon, 1960-1968 (File 5: 30)
  - Taiana, Jorge A., 1968-1972 (File 5: 31)
  - Tidona, Juan, 1963 (File 5: 32)
  - Torrijos, Omar, circa 1970 (File 5: 33)
  - Trujillo, Rafael, 1958-1961 (File 5: 34)
  - Trujillo (hijo), Rafael L., 1961-1966 (File 5: 35)
  - Unamuno, Juan, 1965-1971 (File 5: 36)
  - Valle, Susana, 1968-1969 (File 5: 37)
  - Vandor, Augusto, 1959-1968 (File 5: 38)
  - Vásquez, Pedro Eladio, 1968 (File 5: 39)
  - Vega Pagan, Coronel, 1959 (File 5: 40)
  - Vicente, Pablo
    - 1958-1959 (File 6: 1)
    - 1964 (File 6: 2)
    - 1965
      - January-February (File 6: 3)
      - March-April (File 6: 4)
      - May-July (File 6: 5)
    - 1966 (File 6: 6)
    - 1967
      - January-April (File 6: 7)
      - May-July (File 6: 8)
      - August-December (File 6: 9)
    - 1968
      - January-February (File 7: 1)
      - March-June (File 7: 2)
      - July-August (File 7: 3)
      - September-December (File 7: 4)
    - 1969
      - April-August (File 7: 5)
      - October-December (File 7: 6)
    - 1970 (File 7: 7)
    - 1971
      - January-June (File 8: 1)
      - July-December (File 8: 2)
    - 1972 (File 8: 3)
  - Villalon, Héctor O., 1963-1972 (File 8: 4)
- Speeches and Writings, 1931-1972 (Box 8)
  Contains articles, course outlines, and interviews, arranged chronologically.
  - Guerra ruso-japonesa, course outlines, Escuela Superior de Guerra, Buenos Aires, Argentina, 1931-1933 (File 8: 5)
    Holographs and typescripts
  - Actitud oportunista de Estados Unidos frente al desarrollo económico de la Ameríca Latina, circa 1949 (File 8: 6)
    Typescript
  - Algo más sobre confederaciones continentales, circa 1950 (File 8: 7)
    Holograph
  - Cooperación económica, circa 1950 (File 8: 8)
  - Solidaridad continental, circa 1950 (File 8: 9)
  - La situación argentina, circa 1956 (File 8: 10)
  - Como se entrega un país, 1956 September 29 (File 8: 11)
  - Asilados, refugiados y exiliados políticos, circa 1957 (File 8: 12)
  - ¿Que pasa con la economía argentina?, circa 1957 (File 8: 13)
  - Answers to questionnaire, Diário Trabalhista (Rio de Janeiro), 1957 January 15 (File 8: 14)
  - ¿Qué pasa con la política argentina?, 1957 March 31 (File 8: 15)
    Typescript and printed copy
  - La tragedia del peso argentino, 1957 May (File 8: 16)
  - Al pueblo argentino, circa 1958 (File 8: 17)
  - Hablemos claro, circa 1958 (File 8: 18)
  - El poder del inepcia, circa 1958 (File 8: 19)
  - El valor del peso argentine-una mentira más, circa 1958 (File 8: 20)
  - Preface to a book by Américo Barrios, 1959 June 30 (File 8: 21)
  - Article on Arturo Frondizi and his relations with the Peronist movement, circa 1960 (File 8: 22)
    Typescript drafts
  - Jules Dubois y América Latina, circa 1960 (File 8: 23)
  - La justicia: una infamia más de la dictadura argentina, circa 1960 (File 8: 24)
  - Series of articles written under the pseudonym "Descartes,", circa 1962
    - Reportage al General Perón, unnumbered (File 8: 25)
    - Decadencia de Occidente, no. 1 (File 8: 26)
    - Amigos dociles, no. 2 (File 8: 27)
    - La dictadura del capitalismo, no. 3 (File 8: 28)
    - Intervención extranjera, no. 4 (File 8: 29)
    - Política y petroleo, no. 5 (File 8: 30)
    - Intervención foranea en la política interna, no. 6 (File 8: 31)
    - La ayuda internacional y la justicia social, no. 7 (File 8: 32)
    - Democracías totalitarias, no. 8 (File 8: 33)
    - La lucha capitalista contra el comunismo, no. 9 (File 8: 34)
    - Idiotas utiles, no. 10 (File 8: 35)
    - Dime con quién andas…, no. 11 (File 8: 36)
  - Unidad, solidaridad y organización, circa 1970 (File 8: 37)
  - Elecciones internas, Las bases, circa 1972 (File 8: 38)
  - La escuela sofística, circa 1972 (File 8: 39)
  - Los militares han agarrado un tigre por la cula: Ahora tienen el problema de largarlo, circa 1972 (File 8: 40)
  - El asunto de los acuerdos, Las bases, 1972 February 20 (File 8: 41)
  - La juventud en el frente, Las bases, 1972 March 20 (File 8: 42)
- Peronist Movement File, 1956-1988 (Boxes 9-10)
  Contains articles, clippings, communiqués, correspondence, declarations, directives, and reports, arranged alphabetically by name.
  - Barrios, Américo, 1958 (File 9: 1)
    Articles and interviews with Juan Péron.
  - Lopez Rega, José, 1971-1972
    - Articles and speeches, circa 1972 (File 9: 2)
    - Correspondence, 1971-1972 (File 9: 3)
  - Perón, Eva, circa 1950 (File 9: 4)
    Holograph statement of her belief in Peronism.
  - Perón, Isabel, 1965-1988
    - Articles and speeches, 1972 (File 9: 5)
    - Clippings, 1965 (File 9: 6)
    - Correspondence, 1971-1989 (File 9: 7)
  - Perón, Juan, 1957-1972
    - Communiqués, declarations, and open letters
      - 1956-1961 (File 9: 8)
      - 1962-1969 (File 9: 9)
    - Directives and instructions, 1957-1972 (File 9: 10)
    - Memoranda, circa 1957-1963 (File 9: 11)
    - Reports, 1958-1959 (File 9: 12)
  - Other individuals and organizations, 1957-1972
    - Clippings, 1971 (File 9: 13)
    - Declarations, 1963-1972 (File 9: 14)
    - Leaflets, 1965-1969 (File 9: 15)
    - Memoranda, 1971 (File 9: 16)
    - Pamphlets, 1964-1966 (File 9: 17)
    - Reports, 1957-1969 (File 10: 1)
    - Song lyrics, 1967 (File 10: 2)
    - Speeches, 1969-1971 (File 10: 3)
    - Statement of principles, 1971 (File 10: 4)
- Subject File, 1945-1971 (Box 10)
  Includes articles and clippings, arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Argentina - politics and government, 1956-1968 (File 10: 5)
  - Club del 45, circa 1945 (File 10: 6)
  - Molinas Rio de la Plata S.A., 1971 (File 10: 7)
  - Premoli, Luis Máximo, circa 1958 (File 10: 8)
- Photographs, 1950-1960 (Box 10)
  Contains prints depicting Juan and Eva Perón.
  - Perón, Eva, circa 1950 (File 10: 9)
    One print
  - Perón, Juan, 1951-1960 (File 10: 10)
    Eight prints
- Printed Matter, 1954-2002 (Box 10)
  Includes monographs and serial issues, arranged by physical form.
  - Monographs relating to Eva Perón, 1944-2002 (File 10: 11-12)
  - Serial issues, 1954-1988 (File 10: 13)
  - Photocopies of letters and newspaper clippings, CDs, 1956-1960, 1972-1976, undated (File 10: 14)
- Oversize Materials, 1950-1974 (Boxes 11-12)
  Includes monographs, serial issues, portaits, and a calendar.
  - Serial issue, 1974 (File 11: 1)
  - Monograph relating to social and economic programs of Peronist government, 1950 (File 11: 2)
  - Portrait of Juan Perón, circa 1950 (File 11: 3)
  - Portraits, 1952-1961
    - Perón, Eva, 1952 (File 12: 1)
    - Perón, Juan, 1961 (File 12: 2)
  - Calendar with portraits of Juan Perón, 1953 (File 12: 3)
- Declassified U.S. Government Records, 1959 (Box 10)
  Formerly security-classified records of the U.S. government, released in full or in part. Arranged chronologically by date of release by Hoover.
  - 2015 December release of records, 1959 (Box-folder 10: 15)
    Photocopies of U.S. Department of State Foreign Service despatches. One from the American Embassy in Buenos Aires to the Department of State, dated 14 September 1959, has the subject "Dominican Foreign Minister Promises Action Against Peron." The other, from the American Embassy in Ciudad Trujillo [Dominican Republic] to the Department of State, dated 14 October 1959, has the subject "Conversation with Acting Foreign Minister Balaguer," and includes a memorandum of conversation between Vice President Joaquin Balaguer and Henry Dearborn (Chargé d'Affaires).